<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info xml:lang="en">
    <div class="title">Documentation</div>
    <h2>Welcome to CMDRSB - the application trinity serving CLARIN Metadata</h2>
    <p>
        <strong>CMDRSB</strong> consists of
	  <ul>
            <li>
                <strong>Metadata Repository</strong> where all the metadata records are stored,</li>
            <li>the <strong>Metadata Service</strong> providing a REST-style interface allowing to access programmaticaly the information stored in the Repository</li>
            <li>and the <strong>Metadata Browser</strong> a user-interface for exploring the Repository.</li>
        </ul>
    </p>
    <p>Some further resources about <strong>CMDRSB</strong>:
		<ul>
            <li>
                <a target="_blank" href="/MDService2/static/CMDRSB_20110123.pdf">Presentation about CMDRSB at CMDI-Workshop, Nijmegen 2011-01-17</a>
            </li>
            <li>
                <a target="_blank" href="/MDService2/static/MDService2.wadl">WADL-file</a> describing the REST-interface of MDService (<a href="/MDService2/static/MDService2.wadl.html">HTML-version</a>) </li>
            <li>
                <a href="/MDService2/docs/htmlpage/data">Data statistics</a> -  some numbers about the current dataset in the repository</li>
        </ul>
    </p>
    <div id="introduction">
        <h3>Overview</h3>
        <p>Summary of available functionality of the MDBrowser:
	 <ul>
                <li>simple search (simple terms, combined terms, phrases)</li>
                <li>complex boolean-searches (according to the SRU/CQL standard)</li>
                <li>browsing the collections</li>
                <li>browsing the (aggregated) xml-structure of the MD records (under "Terms")</li>
                <li>search by profiles</li>
                <li>search by data categories</li>
                <li>perform semantic search (elements of individual CMD-profiles are related via ConceptLinks to Data Categories, 
			which are in turn related in the <strong>Relation Registry</strong>)</li>
                <li>view individual metadata records </li>
                <li>work with multiple queries and resultsets in parallel</li>
                <li>page through the results</li>
                <li>dynamically change the columns displaying the fields of the records</li>
                <li>use auto-columns (if you select no columns, MDService will try to select the 6 most useful)</li>
            </ul>
        </p>
        <div>
            <p>Explanation of the usage/functionality of individual user-interface elements:</p>
            <a target="_blank" href="/MDService2/static/MDBrowser_explained_5_resize2000.png">
                <img src="/MDService2/static/MDBrowser_explained_5_resize800.png" title="MDBrowser explained2"/>
            </a>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div id="ui-info">
        <h2>User-Interface explained</h2>
        <div id="serverqs-info">
            <h3>Public space / Options / Profile</h3>
            <p>Space meant for News, as Dashboard, for common sample queries or as options-window. Currently no function.</p>
        </div>
        <div id="userqs-info">
            <h3>Personalized workspace - commons</h3>
            <p>When logged in, you can store your queries and bookmarks here.</p>
            <p>All anonymous users share the default workspace.</p>
        </div>
        <div id="collections-info">
            <h3>Collections</h3>
            <p>Overview of collections=datasets available in the repository.</p>
        </div>
        <div id="terms-info">
            <h3>Terms</h3>
            <p>Terms combine information from MDRepository, <em>Component Registry</em>, Data Category Registries (<a target="_blank" href="http://www.isocat.org">isocat</a>, <a target="_blank" href="http://dublincore.org/">dublincore</a>) 
				and Relation Registry to allow to search by profiles or data categories, or even perform semantic search.</p>
            <p>Thus you can search in the fields of individual profiles instantiated as the MDrecords in the repository, or search over multiple profiles via data categories.</p>
        </div>
        <div id="compreg-info">
            <h3>Component Registry</h3>
            <p>Overview of all profiles and components defined in the Component Registry. (Proxy to Component Registry)</p>
        </div>
        <div id="query-input-info">
            <h3>Query Input</h3>
            <p>Form for entering the query. Either a simple or complex query. 
			See <a href="/MDService2/docs/htmlpage/queries">example queries</a> for an overview of possible query types.</p>
            <dl>
                <dt id="input-simplequery-info">simple full-text search</dt>
                <dd>individual terms, multiple terms, phrases</dd>
                <dt id="searchclauselist-info">complex queries</dt>
                <dd>complex queries according to SRU/CQL-standard
					<p>Basic <em>search clause</em> consists of: <code>index relation term</code>, e.g. <code>dc.title any system</code>.
					You can combine these search clauses with boolean operators (AND, OR), to more complex queries. </p>
                </dd>
            </dl>
            <p>Both parts can be used in parallel - i.e. you can specify some terms for full-text search
			and further refine them with filters on specific indices - 
			the two parts being combined with boolean AND (the matching records have to satisfy both parts of the query.).
			So the <strong>general syntax</strong> of the queries feasible within the query input is:
			<div class="example">simple-query AND (XQ1 or XQ2) AND (XQ3 or XQ4 or ...) AND ...<br/>
				XQ := index relation term   
			</div>
            </p>
            <dl>
                <dt id="repositories_select-info">Repository</dt>
                <dd>
                    <p>You can select target repository(-mirror).</p>
                    <p>The <em>Collections</em> and <em>Terms</em> are updated accordingly (but this can take a few seconds).</p>
                </dd>
                <dt id="input-withsummary-info">with Summary</dt>
                <dd>
                    <p>This option provides a summary of the profiles used in the (whole) result and of the (XML-structure of the) displayed part of the result, but it obviously makes you wait a bit longer (Usually 20-50% penalty on the query-duration, but may be worse for queries returning large results.)</p>
                </dd>
            </dl>
        </div>
        <div id="querylist-info"/>
        <div id="commands">
            <h3>Commands</h3>
            <p>List of commands available in the user-interface, explanation of their function:<br/>
                <span class="note">(if you want to print this, you have to activate: "printing background images" in your browser, to get the icons printed as well.)</span>
            </p>
            <dl>
                <dt id="cmd_add">Add new item</dt>
                <dt id="cmd_add_and">Add an additional condition (AND)</dt>
                <dt id="cmd_add_or">Add a alternative condition (OR)</dt>
                <dt id="cmd_columns">Manage columns/fields</dt>
                <dd>Allows to de/select the columns and change the list-format (list or table).
			It requires the option <em>withSummary</em> to be activated, to provide the list of elements/indices that can be added as columns/fields.</dd>
                <dt id="userqueries.cmd_del" idref="#userqueries .cmd_del">Delete!</dt>
                <dd>Delete the stored query!</dd>
                <dt id="cmd_detail">Show detail information</dt>
                <dt id="cmd_down">Expand view</dt>
                <dt id="cmd_filter">Apply as filter/Use in query</dt>
                <dt id="cmd_get">Loading ...</dt>
                <dt id="cmd_info">Info/Help</dt>
                <dd>Contextual documentation - explanation of the ui/data element in question</dd>
                <dt id="cmd_load">Load query</dt>
                <dd>Load the query and show the result</dd>
                <dt id="cmd_reload">Reload</dt>
                <dt id="cmd_resubmit">Reload</dt>
                <dt id="cmd_save">Store query/bookmark</dt>
                <dd>The query/bookmark will be added to the current Queryset in the <em>Personal Workspace</em>.</dd>
                <dt id="cmd_sc_delete">Remove search clause</dt>
                <dd>if only one search clause - clear it</dd>
                <dt id="cmd_up">Collapse view</dt>
                <dt id="cmd_prev">Page back</dt>
                <dd>Load the previous page of the current result</dd>
                <dt id="cmd_next">Page forward</dt>
                <dd>Load the next page of the current result</dd>
            </dl>
        </div>
    </div>
</info>